Finding Aid for Holmes Family Papers, 1883-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Holmes Family papers, 1883-1957 1897-1903
Holmes Family.
1 linear ft.
861037 Aa 2
Bay City, Michigan. Personal letters, primarily of Susie Holmes living in New York from family members in Michigan detaining daily activities and family matters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Sally Lien (donated no. 7218 ) in June 1985.
The collection is open to research.
The Holmes family lived in turn-of-the century Bay City, Michigan. They were middle-class entrepreneurs in the lumber business, their social circle consisting of other mill and hardware business families. The mother, Emeline, widow of Mr. Henry (?) Holmes, had at least five children: Susie (Susan Ann); John called also Jack and married to Pauline; Wendell, a lumber dealer, married to Ruth Price; Daisy (possibly real name Lydia), a sister (name uncertain) married to Edward C. Hargrave, who was the son in E. J. Hargrave & Son Lumber Mill, with possibly three children; and Harry Holmes who may have been a brother of Henry Holmes.
The Holmes papers, dating ca. 1883 to 1957, have been divided into four major series: Susie Holmes Papers, Harry Holmes Papers, Other Holmes Papers, and Miscellaneous. For the most part, the Holmes Family collection documents events and concerns of a middle-class family running a family business and socializing with other middle-class business families. The family enjoyed good hotels when they traveled, they worried about profits and losses, and they commented occasionally on national events of the times. But in sum, their work ethic, comments about life and death in general, and concern for family and friends are the themes that distinguish this collection of family letters.
The bulk of the papers consists of letters from the family to Susie Holmes. From 1897 to 1903, Susie was living near, and working in, Buffalo New York for Charles G. Butts. In addition to family correspondence, business correspondence from her boss, and personal business material such as her insurance notices, the Susie Holmes series includes church activity announcements, a few wedding invitations, a batch of 3 x 5 cards with English and American literary references, and letters to and from other members of her family which were subsequently forwarded on to Susie.
Subjects:
Bay City (Mich.); Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.; Women--New York (State)
Contributors:
Holmes, Harry.; Holmes, Susie.
- Susie A. Holmes
  The letters to Susie Holmes refer to family and friends, their ailments, travels, moving experiences, comments about the family business, and acknowledgment of gifts received during the holidays. Susie, it would appear, was the only member of the family, with the possible exception of a sibling in Georgia, not living in the Bay City area. Though there is no indication Susie was escaping from an affair of the heart or that she was an early advocate of women's economic rights, she was fairly young, unmarried, and living far from home. The many letters, often dated one day right after the other, indicate a voluminous correspondence between Susie and her family. The series of her business correspondence also indicates that she had a very cordial relationship with her boss and her boss's mother or wife. Susie also received "letters" from a few of her young nieces and nephews. She traveled occasionally to see family members either for brief vacation time or for business, and was trusted enough by her boss, Charles G. Butts, to receive letters from him with instructions to act upon information he was sending her or to look up information for him.
  - Family correspondence, letters addressed to Susie, 1897-1903 and undated, 26 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters forwarded to Susie (with no accompanying-letter), 1900-1903 (Box 1)
  - Postcards, 1900-1903 (Box 1)
  - Telegrams, 1899 ?-1903 (Box 1)
  - Business Correspondence, Letters of Charles G. Butts (Susie's boss) to Susie, 1898-1903, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous insurance forms and letters, 1897-1903 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified, 1902-1903 (Box 1)
  - Wedding invitations (Box 1)
  - Church materials (Box 1)
  - 3 x 5 cards
    - English Literature titles (Box 1)
    - American Literature titles (Box 1)
    - Magazine titles (Box 1)
    - "Captivities" (Box 1)
    - "Travels" (Box 1)
    - Undetermined (Box 1)
- Harry Holmes (primarily receipts), 1883-1913
  The second series of the collection relates to Harry Holmes. Included are business receipts between Harry and other companies dealing in lumber, hardware, brick and tile, lime, machine parts, and other goods and services. There is also a copy of a contract between Harry and the Michigan Central Railroad for the building of a machine shop in Bay City.
  - Personal receipts
    - Handwritten ledgers (Box 1)
    - Newspaper subscriptions (Box 1)
    - Groceries and ice (Box 1)
    - Household goods (such as wall paper) (Box 1)
    - Printers and books (Box 1)
    - Clothes and Shoes (Box 1)
    - Untitled receipts "received of Harry Holmes" (Box 1)
  - Business receipts, alphabetical by name of company
    - A-M (Box 1)
    - N-Z (Box 1)
    - Single, assorted receipts from hardware and lumber related dealers (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous receipts (Box 1)
  - Contract between Harry Holmes and the Michigan Central Railroad for the building of a machine shop in Bay City, Michigan (Box 1)
- Other Correspondence
  Letters to and from other members of the Holmes family, including the Price in-laws, make up the third series.
  - Holmes Family, 1901-1957 (Box 1)
    scattered dates
  - Price Family in-laws, 1924-1944 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The final series contains miscellaneous correspondence from non-relations, fragments of letters (no beginning and/or no date), advertisements, social event announcements, and other ephemeral items.
  - Letters to others and fragments (Box 1)
  - Advertisements and ephemera (Box 1)